בוקר טוב, Boker tov, today's דף daf is כ"ג Chaf Gimmel and
we pick up in the bottom of כ"ה עמוד ב', Chaf Hey
Amud Bais, the two dots, המפלת כמין בהמה, Hamapeles kemin behemah, about
ten lines before the line begins to get wide. And as I
said, the entire פרק Perek is dealing with issues about when a
woman is considered a יולדת, yoledet, has the טומאה tuma of childbirth,
and that includes cases of miscarriage. We had a lot of discussion
about when it's not a fetus, but do we assume that when
things are expelled from the uterus that necessarily blood comes out? And
even if blood does come out, we had a whole discussion about
whether it's an issue of whether it comes out not directly touching
the vaginal wall or not in a natural way. But now we
turn to the main focus of what constitutes a fetus in order
to create, in order to define the woman as having given birth
for the purposes of being טמאה tmeiah as a יולדת, yoledet, which
also has relevance nowadays because that טומאה tuma of יולדת yoledet also
means, like טומאה tuma of נדה, niddah, that there's a prohibition of
sex. So the child does not have to actually be viable, it
could even be a miscarriage, but it does have to
have a human appearance. And the משנה Mishna said if it looks
like fish, no, if it looks like בהמה behemah or חיה, chayah,
some type of a mammal, then רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir said that
would be considered a fetus for this הלכה halacha and the חכמים
chachamim said no. So let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara.
המפלת כמין בהמה, Hamapeles kemin behemah, if it looks like a בהמה.
behemah. אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל, Amar Rav Yehuda Amar Shmuel, מאי
טעמא דרבי מאיר, Mai ta'ama deRebbi Meir, what's the reason of רבי
מאיר Rebbi Meir that he considers even if it doesn't have human
form to have a הלכה halakhic status of a fetus? I am
going to assume by the way for the sake of argument that
the
rabbis were assuming that this actually was a human fetus, but it
just had for some reason missed its form, okay, as opposed to
some idea that maybe actually some animal fetus somehow magically appeared in
a woman's uterus. Okay, so I mentioned that because we might see
some גמרות Gemaras later that a little bit challenge that, but for
now let's just assume that it's just a question of appearance, not
of the actual nature of the thing.
Similar to discussions for example like we had about blood, it's not
a question about the biological nature, sometimes there are issues about appearance
that define its הלכה halakhic status.
Are you saying that's your interpretation?
I think the גמרא Gemara is ambiguous. Here certainly all it's talking
about is כמין בהמה, kemin behemah, כמין חיה, kemin chayah, it looks
like a בהמה, behemah, it looks like a חיה. chayah. The reason
I am saying this is that it will be a later גמרא
Gemara that will ask some questions that seem to...
but I'm not assuming that it's a human...
no, no, no, the literal language is the fetus looks כמין חיה,
kemin chayah, like a חיה. chayah. Now, like a בהמה. behemah. So
I don't... I think the משנה Mishna could be... certainly there's nothing
I would say in the משנה Mishna that indicates that it thinks
it's not human. But we will see language later that indicates that
maybe it was actually thinking that it's not actually human. But for
now I will assume that that is not the case. So let's
take a look. So מאי טעמא דרבי מאיר, Mai ta'ama deRebbi Meir,
what's the reason of רבי מאיר? Rebbi Meir? וייצר ה' אלקים את
כל חית השדה ואת כל עוף השמים, Vayyitzer Hashem Elokim et kol
chayat hasadeh ve'et kol oph hashamayim, because when on the fifth day
when it says God created the animals, it says וייצר ה' אלקים
את כל חית השדה ואת כל עוף השמים, Vayyitzer Hashem Elokim et
kol chayat hasadeh ve'et kol oph hashamayim, right, that was in פרק
ב' Perek Beis I think anyway, that God was וייצר, vayyitzer, God
was fashioned, which is the same phrase that it uses by God
creating humans, thank you. And
therefore it's sort of somewhat in the same category as humans, so
if it has this type of appearance, it does not change its
status. So the גמרא Gemara says... so that includes birds and mammals,
but not fish, which never uses the phrase, right, וייצר. vayyitzer. Right,
what does it say when it says God created the fish? It
says ישרצו המים שרץ נפש חיה, Yishretzu hamayim sheretz nefesh chayah, right,
let the water steam forth. The עוף oph actually I'm sorry, I'm
sorry, by birds... excuse me, excuse me, the משנה Mishna says, what
does the משנה Mishna say? It says
yeah, עוף oph is included because in what would make it... would
make it considered according to רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir considered a human
fetus. Let's take a look at the two פרקים Prakim in בראשית.
Bereishis. In פרק א' Perek Aleph it says,
right, what's it
say? It says ישרצו המים שרץ נפש חיה ועוף יעופף על הארץ,
Yishretzu hamayim sheretz nefesh chayah ve'oph ye'opheph al ha'aretz, so let the
water steam forth. Then it says ויברא את התנינים הגדולים, Vayyivra et
hatanninim hagedolim, the word uses the word creation by the sea monsters,
we'll get back to that. But then it
says אשר שרצו המים למיניהם, Asher shartzu hamayim l'mineihem, etc., etc. So
the primary verb there is ישרצו. yishretzu. Whereas when it comes to
the animals, here it says on day five, תוצא הארץ נפש חיה
למינה, Totzei ha'aretz nefesh chayah l'minah, let the land sort of bring
forth. But then it says ויעש אלקים את חית הארץ למינה ואת
הבהמה למינה, Vaya'as Elokim et chayat ha'aretz l'minah ve'et habehemah l'minah, etc.,
וירא אלקים כי טוב. Vayar Elokim ki tov. Now nevertheless ויעש vaya'as
is not a... now when it comes to humans it says, right,
ויברא אלקים, Vayyivra Elokim, ברא bara God created, etc. So there it's
not the same verbs. By the fish it's ישרצו, yishretzu, by the
animals it's ויעש, vaya'as, and by the humans it's ויברא. vayyivra. But
when you move to the second פרק Perek of בראשית Bereishis we
have, what does it say?
וייצר ה' אלהים Vayiyetzer Hashem Elokim
in פסוק
י"ט pasuk
yud tet
מן האדמה כל חית השדה ואת כל עוף השמים ויבא אל האדם
לראות מה יקרא לו. min haadamah kol chayat hasadeh veet kol of
hashamayim vayavei el haadam lirot mah yikra lo. So it uses at
least in the second פרק, perek, in פרק א' perek aleph it
uses different verbs: וישרצו, Vayishretzu, ויעש, vayaas, ויברא; vayivra; different verbs for
each category. But in the second פרק, perek, it says וייצר Vayiyetzer
God fashioned אדם, Adam, and it says וייצר Vayiyetzer God fashioned בהמה
behemah and עוף. of. Okay, so that's why it's saying that since
it uses the same verb in the second פרק, perek, they are
considered to be somewhat of similar form and consider that these types
of forms it would still be considered a human fetus. So that's
why Rabbi Meir says his position. So now the גמרא Gemara says,
אלא מעתה, Ela meata, if that's true, המפלת דמות תנינים תהא אמו
טמאה לידה. Hamapelet demut taninim tehei imo tmeiah leida. Okay, what I
sort of just indicated, if the animal looks like some type of
a sea monster or, you know, whatever תנינים taninim means, I don't
know, a serpent, a sea serpent, so let the mother be טמאה
לידה tmeiah leida because דנאמר בו יצירה כאדם, denemar bo yetzirah keadam,
since it says the same verb, not יצירה, yetzirah, but it says
the same verb, ויברא, vayivra, כשנאמר ויברא אלהים את התנינים הגדולים, kshenemar
vayivra Elokim et hataninim hagedolim, God created the big sea monsters, and
it says ויברא vayivra by humans obviously. So אמרי, amri, so the
answer is דנין יצירה מיצירה ואין דנין בריאה מיצירה. danin yetzirah miyetzirah
veein danin briah miyetzirah. So first the גמרא Gemara is not acknowledging
that it says בריאה briah by אדם, Adam, which is pretty obvious
and we'll get there, but focusing on the וייצר Vayiyetzer by אדם,
Adam, so we'd rather connect וייצר Vayiyetzer to וייצר Vayiyetzer and not
וייצר Vayiyetzer to ויברא. vayivra. Okay, but then it's obviously going to
move to the next question. First of all, מאי נפקא מינה? mai
nafka mina? Who cares? It all means the same. התם דבי רבי
ישמעאל, Hatam devei Rebbe Yishmael, you know, you don't have to be
so exact by גזירה שוה. gezeirah shavah. The גמרא Gemara asks: ושב
הכהן veshav hakohen ובא הכהן. uva hakohen. And the כהן kohen will
return, the כהן kohen will come. This is by צרעת. tzaraat. זו
היא שיבה זו היא ביאה. Zu heeshivah zu hee beeh. They both
refer to coming back to the house, it just uses different verbs.
But even though it uses different verbs, since the point is the
same, you can make a גזירה שוה. gezeirah shavah. Now that's never
a good question because the גמרא Gemara always says, okay, if you
have no other choice, then it doesn't have to be precise, but
you would certainly much more prefer a precise match than an imprecise
match. Okay, so if you have the word וייצר Vayiyetzer by humans,
ויברא vayivra by monsters, sea monsters, and וייצר Vayiyetzer by other animals,
we'd rather connect it to the וייצר Vayiyetzer rather than an imprecise
match. But the better question is, come on, it says ויברא vayivra
by humans as well. So that's the next
question: ועוד נימר בריאה מבריאה דכתיב ויברא אלהים את האדם בצלמו, veod
nimer briah mibriah dichtiv vayivra Elokim et haadam betzalmo, right? If I
asked you what verb does it say by humans, probably first thing
you would have said is ויברא, vayivra, not וייצר. Vayiyetzer. Right? That's
the most sort of... so anyway... oh, you would have? Okay, fine.
Anyway, so, okay, so anyway we have two verbs by humans, ויברא
vayivra and וייצר. Vayiyetzer. We have a verb by sea monsters, ויברא,
vayivra, and a verb in the second פרק perek by animals and
birds, וייצר. Vayiyetzer. So why not connect the ויברא vayivra both ways
and have all of those things included? So the גמרא Gemara says,
אמרי ויברא לגופיה. amri vayivra legufei. No, no, no. One of the
verbs you need to tell you, you know, the content of the
verse itself, that God created them. You can't use it for גזירה
שוה gezeirah shavah because it's being used already. It's being used to
deliver the message of the פסוק. pasuk.
But isn't the same for all the rest of them?
No. Let's take a look. וייצר לאפנויי. Vayiyetzer leafnuyei. וייצר Vayiyetzer is
extra. Once it had one verb by humans, it didn't need the
second verb. Although it's a little problem because the second verb is
written twenty פסוקים pesukim later, but anyway, so that second verb, maybe
the fact that it switched verbs, that's seen as extra. And therefore
we use the וייצר, Vayiyetzer, not the ויברא. vayivra. And therefore ודאני
יצירה מיצירה, vadani yetzirah miyetzirah, therefore
we use the יצירה yetzirah verb. So the גמרא Gemara says, אדרבה
וייצר לגופיה ויברא לאפנויי. adraba vayiyetzer legufei vayivra leafnuyei. Say the opposite:
וייצר Vayiyetzer is to tell you the content of the פסוק, pasuk,
and ויברא vayivra is the extra verb. So how do you know
which one is serving its, you know, intrinsic purpose and which one
is extra for the linking? So the גמרא Gemara says, ודני בריאה
מבריאה. vedani briah mibriah. Let's therefore use the ויברא vayivra verb to
connect it to the sea monsters. אלא, Ela, so the גמרא Gemara
says fine, you're right. Both in theory could be used. But here's
the difference why we prefer to focus on וייצר: Vayiyetzer:
וייצר מופנה משני צדדים. Vayiyetzer mufne mishnei tzdadim. וייצר Vayiyetzer is open
at both ends. And the גמרא Gemara is about to introduce why
any of this matters, but basically it's extra by humans, so that
means it's free to make a link, to make a גזירה שוה,
gezeirah shavah, and it's extra by the animals, because by the animals
as well it didn't need to say the word וייצר Vayiyetzer and
it allows me to link. Now you have to understand that part
of what the גמרא Gemara sort of is doing here is that
גזירה שוה gezeirah shavah is the most arbitrary of all of the,
you know, י"ג מדות. yud gimmel middot. I mean, you have one
word here, one word there, you make a link. You know, could
be completely different contexts, completely different principles. So that's one of the
sort of checks on that is that you need to have a,
you know, גזירה שוה, gezeirah shavah, you need to have a tradition
about it. Although it's interesting because you have גמרות Gemaras like this
that say why not do it this way, do it this way,
why isn't the answer to all those גמרות Gemaras because that wasn't
my tradition. I had this tradition, not that one. So the רמב"ן
Ramban actually asks this, and not here but elsewhere, the רמב"ן Ramban
says obviously the tradition was not so precise. The tradition was
more... the exact figuring out what the גזירה שוה Gezerah Shavah was
still a little bit up for grabs, so the גמרא Gemara asks
these types of questions. But nevertheless, because גזירה שוה Gezerah Shavah is
so arbitrary, it seems that the
גמרא Gemara understands that there has to be some limits. And the
first limit is, if the, you know, that it's much easier to
learn גזירה שוה Gezerah Shavah if you could argue that the word
is extra. If the word is extra, then I could say, oh,
so it's extra, it's here to create a link to something else.
And it's even better if the word in this category is extra
and the word in that category is extra. If they're both extra,
they're the same words, that at least is suggesting let's see them
as creating some link. If one is extra and the other isn't,
it's a weaker link. If neither are extra, but it's the same
words, that's the weakest. So that's called מופנה משני צדדים mufneh mishnei
tzdadim meaning both words are, each, the word in each category, you
know, the same word, but in the two different categories, in the
two different פרשיות parshiyot are seen as each one is seen as
extra. מופנה מצד אחד mufneh mitzad echad means one of them is
seen as extra, the other one is not. And if it's not
מופנה כל עיקר mufneh kol ikar means that both words are doing
their normal function in the פסוקים psukim but they happen to be
the same word. So obviously the first is the easiest to make
the גזירה שוה, gezerah shavah, the last is the hardest. So that's
what it's saying. It's saying when it comes to ויצר, Vayitzer, it
didn't need to say it by humans, it didn't need to say
it by animals, and that allows for a strong link. Let's see
why that's true. So it says like this, אלא ויצר Ella Vayitzer
the first of the middle sized lines, אלא ויצר מופנה משני צדדים.
Ella Vayitzer mufneh mishnei tzdadim. ויצר Vayitzer is open at both ends.
מופנה מגבי אדם, Mufneh migabei Adam, it's open by the humans, because
we already said it could have just said ויברא Vayivra and it
says ויצר, Vayitzer, so you could argue the opposite, but it's possible
it's open by humans. ומופנה מגבי בהמה Umufneh migabei behemah and it's
free by בהמה behemah because as we'll see in a minute there's
another verb by בהמה. behemah. ויברא גבי אדם מופנה, Vayivra gabei Adam
mufneh, ויברא Vayivra it's true you could argue it's free by humans
because maybe ויצר Vayitzer is doing the real work and ויברא Vayivra
is open. But גבי תנינים אינו מופנה, gabei taninim eino mufneh, there's
no other verb by the sea monsters. There's only one verb by
the sea monsters, ויברא. Vayivra. So therefore the ויברא Vayivra of the
sea monsters can never be considered to be open and free. But
by all the other things, the animals and humans and so on,
there are other verbs doing the work and you didn't necessarily need
these words. So the גמרא Gemara says, מאי מופנה גבי בהמה? Mai
mufneh gabei behemah? Where is it extra? We already said it's extra
by humans because the work could be done by the word ויברא.
Vayivra. So where can the work be done by בהמה? behemah? אילימא
מדכתיב ויעש אלקים את חית הארץ, Ilima midechtiv Vayaas Elokim et chayat
haaretz, God made and he uses the verb ויעש, Vayaas, the animals.
וכתיב ויצר ה' אלקים מן האדמה כל חית השדה, Uchtiv Vayitzer Hashem
Elokim min haadamah kol chayat hasadeh, and then it says ויצר. Vayitzer.
So because it has a different verb ויעש Vayaas that's doing the
work, ויצר Vayitzer is seen as free. Okay, is the point clear
here? Meaning it's better if the verb is extra. By humans it
has ויברא, Vayivra, so we could argue ויצר Vayitzer is extra. By
animals it says ויעש, Vayaas, so we could argue ויצר Vayitzer is
extra. Both of the same words could be argued are extra, that
makes a strong link. So the גמרא Gemara says if that's true,
גבי תנינא נמי לופני. gabei tanina nami lifnei. I'll argue that the
sea monsters, the word ויברא Vayivra is also extra.
Why is it free? דכתיב ואת כל רמש האדמה. Dechtiv ve'et kol
remes ha'adamah. It says that God created in that verse all of
the things that creep on the ground, וכתיב ויברא אלקים את התנינים
הגדולים. Uchtiv Vayivra Elokim et hataninim hagedolim. So and God made the
sea monsters. It's assuming, which is a strange assumption,
it's assuming, yes it is,
no it doesn't, ויברא אלקים את התנינים הגדולים ואת כל נפש החיה
הרמשת אשר שרצו המים, Vayivra Elokim et hataninim hagedolim ve'et kol nefesh
hachayah haromeset asher shirtzu hamayim, right, ואת כל עוף כנף, ve'et kol
of kanaf, right, למינהו, leminehu, what's your problem? It doesn't say in
that פסוק pasuk ואת,
what was it?
ואת כל רמש האדמה.
Ve'et kol remes
ha'adamah
No, Michael, that wasn't the פסוק pasuk we were quoting. ואת כל
רמש האדמה remes ha'adamah, is the verse by ויצר. Vayitzer. So you
already have the verse by ויצר Vayitzer by רמש האדמה, remes ha'adamah,
so you don't need the word ויברא Vayivra by תנינים. taninim. So
it's assuming for some reason that תנינים taninim are רמש remes, האדמה,
which is a bizarre, I know, a whole question, which is a
bizarre assumption. So the גמרא Gemara says no, רמש דכתיב התם דיבשה
הוא. Remes dechtiv hatam dyabashah hu. No, obviously there, yes, it's in
that, you have that word ויצר Vayitzer by רמש, but that's not
relevant to the sea monsters because the sea monsters are not land
animals, so it's not extra. Okay, תוספות Tosafot even asks what was
the question? Anyway, so that's the answer. The answer is that by
sea monsters the word is the only verb and therefore it's not
free. By the case of humans and חיה, chayah, there are other
verbs available and you have an extra, could be argued an extra
verb of ויצר Vayitzer in both categories and that allows you to
make a link. So now the גמרא Gemara says, and now the
גמרא Gemara interestingly gets into this sort of more abstract question about
the strength of a גזירה שוה. gezerah shavah. ומאי
נפקא מינה בין מופנה מצד אחד למופנה משני צדדים? Umai nafkamina bein
mufneh mitzad echad lemufneh mishnei tzdadim? What do I care if it's
free on one side or free on both sides? No, נפקא מינה,
nafkamina, there's a difference. דאמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל משום רבי ישמעאל,
De'amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel mishum Rabi Yishmael, in the name of
רבי ישמעאל, Rabi Yishmael, כל גזירה שוה שאינה מופנה כל עיקר. Kol
gezerah shavah she'eina mufneh kol ikar. Now it's interesting because you know
that
רבי ישמעאל Rabi Yishmael is one of the people that articulates the
principles of the way the תורה Torah is נדרש. nidrash. But there
is some question about whether those belong there because we're going to
see the continuation. continuation of this statement is going to reference רבי
ישמעאל. Rabbi Yishmael. So those words might be inserted. Anyway, כל גזירה
שוה שאינה מופנה כל עיקר אין למידין הימנה. Kol gezera shava she'eina
mufne kol ikkar ein lemedin heimena. If neither words are open, you
cannot make a גזירה שוה. gezera shava. But we said it's very
arbitrary, so at least you need one word open. Open, מופנה מצד
אחד, mufne mitzad echad, one of the words is considered to be
available for use, then לרבי ישמעאל למידין ואין משיבין. le-Rabbi Yishmael lemedin
ve-ein meshivin. So then he had a tradition. רש"י Rashi said this
is not based on any other source, this is the tradition that
שמואל Shmuel had, that there was a debate of רבי ישמעאל Rabbi
Yishmael and the רבנן, Rabbanan, one would assume רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva,
about what is your sort of scope here, what's your ability to
use this גזירה שוה. gezera shava. So if one of the words
is available, למידין ואין משיבין. lemedin ve-ein meshivin. You can make the
גזירה שוה gezera shava and I don't—I'm not concerned with any logical
questions, it's a strong גזירה שוה. gezera shava. רבנן, Rabbanan, the Rabbis
who would argue would say למידין ומשיבין. lemedin u-meshivin. Yes, you can
make גזירה שוה, gezera shava, but it is vulnerable to attacks and
to critique. So again, this points to the idea that the גמרא
Gemara recognizes that גזירה שוה gezera shava is very arbitrary. So therefore,
if you have—even if you have—A, you can't do it at all
if you don't have one word available; B, if you have one
word available you can do it, but if any good logical question
can be raised to challenge the validity of the גזירה שוה, gezera
shava, like how does it make sense to apply this to this,
then it doesn't hold water. Any critique will destroy it, okay? If
it only is one word available. Except רבי ישמעאל, Rabbi Yishmael, רבי
ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael says even one word is enough. According to the
Rabbis, it's open to critique.
מופנה משני צדדין, mufne mishnei tzedadin, if it's available on both sides,
דברי הכל למידין ואין משיבין. divei hakol lemedin ve-ein meshivin. And everybody
would agree that that is a watertight גזירה שוה. gezera shava. I
don't care if there's logical questions, I'm allowed to make it if
both words are available on both ends. All right, so now the
גמרא Gemara says: רבי ישמעאל מאי איכא בין מופנה מצד אחד למופנה
משני צדדין? Rabbi Yishmael mai ika bein mufne mitzad echad le-mufne mishnei
tzedadin? Since רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael says that if one word is
available it's watertight, so what difference is one word available or two
words available? Is there a difference between choosing one or the other?
Because we just right now said we'd rather learn out from animals
rather than the sea monsters because one has two words available and
one has one. So according to רבי ישמעאל, Rabbi Yishmael, what difference
does it make? So the גמרא Gemara says: נפקא מינה. Nafka mina.
No, it makes exactly this difference. דהיכא דאיכא מופנה מצד אחד ומופנה
משני צדדין, De-heicha de-ika mufne mitzad echad u-mufne mishnei tzedadin, if you
can choose which type of גזירה שוה gezera shava do I want
to make, one that uses both words available or one that only
has one word available, שבקינן מופנה מצד אחד—we shafkinan mufne mitzad echad
abandon the case of only
one—דף daf. כ"ב ע"א—וילפינן מופנה משני צדדין, mufne mishnei tzedadin, and we
learn out from both words available. So again, the גמרא Gemara is
saying why not learn out—it uses the same verb by sea monsters?
And the answer is yes, but there the verb is not as
available, and therefore we would always rather make a גזירה שוה gezera
shava with when both ends are available rather than only one end
is available, and therefore we are not using it by sea monsters,
this idea of the shape of the fetus. So now the גמרא
Gemara says and ends this by saying exactly that: ולהכי אפניה רחמנא
לבהמה משני צדדין. Ve-lahachi afneih Rachmana le-vehema mishnei tzedadin. That's why it
made the—the word by בהמה, behema, the ויצר, vayitzer, available at both
ends, by the בהמה behema and by the humans, in order to
tell you: כי היכי דלא ניגמר ממופנה מצד אחד. Ki heichi de-lo
nigmar mi-mufne mitzad echad. To tell you don't learn out from the
sea monsters. If you're going to connect humans, connect them to the
animals and therefore—and not to the sea monsters, and your hint to
that is that both words are extra—it's extra at both ends. And
now the גמרא Gemara says, רב אחא—just Rav Acha to end up
this issue about the when do we make גזירה שוה—רב אחא בריה
דרבא מתני לה בשמיה דרבי אליעזר לקולא. le-kula, So רב אחא בריה
דרבא Rav Acha brei de-Rava says the same discussion in the name
of רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, לקולא, lenient. Now I should say this
is an interesting use of the word lenient. Lenient more means like
we're going to go easy on you. But here it's not a
question about going easy. Here it just more means like sort of
like—like lower standards. You'll see what I mean. So let's—let's see. Because
it's not about practically whether it makes your life harder or difficult.
Here's what he says about the parameters: כל גזירה שוה שאינה מופנה
כל עיקר, Kol gezera shava she-eina mufne kol ikkar,
if—if neither word is available, למידין ומשיבין. lemedin u-meshivin. You can make
a גזירה שוה gezera shavas even with no words, even if both
words are doing—are doing their job, you know, in the verses, they're
not really free. Nevertheless, you can make it, but it's open to
critique. מופנה מצד אחד, mufne mitzad echad, if one word is free,
then לרבי ישמעאל למידין ואין משיבין. le-Rabbi Yishmael lemedin ve-ein meshivin. Then
according to רבי ישמעאל, Rabbi Yishmael, you make it and it's watertight,
no critique is accepted—is accepted. לרבנן למידין ומשיבין. le-Rabbanan lemedin u-meshivin. The
רבנן Rabbanan
you make it and again it remains open to critique. Doesn't seem
to be a difference between zero and one for the רבנן. Rabbanan.
מופנה mufneh, משני צדדין, if both words are open, דברי הכל למידין
ואין משיבין. divei hakol lemedin ve-ein meshivin. Everybody agrees that then it's
a גזירה שוה gezera shava that you can make and that is
watertight. So the only way this is different is what happens if
neither word is available. The first approach said neither word is available,
no גזירה שוה. gezera shava This said neither word is available, yes
גזירה שוה gezera shava. but open to critique. Now you see what
I mean that קולא kula here doesn't normally mean what it means.
It doesn't—if you're making a גזירה שוה, gezera shava it doesn't tell
me if at the end of the day it's going to make
my life easier or harder. קולא kula just means that we're more
sort of inclusive in our standards, we're more free to make גזירה
שוה. gezera shava, We can even make them if both words—if neither
word is available. So now the גמרא Gemara just ends this by
saying: ולרבנן, Ve-la-Rabbanan, so according to this version that if zero is
available or one is available You can make it and critique it,
what's the difference between zero or one? ולרבנן U'lerabbanan says the גמרא,
Gemara, I lost my
place, ולרבנן. U'lerabbanan.
Okay, ולרבנן מאי איכא בין מופנה מצד אחד ואינו מופנה כל עיקר?
U'lerabbanan mai ika bein mufneh mitzad echad v'eino mufneh kol ikar? What
difference does it make? If zero you make and critique and one
you make and critique, what difference does it make? So you obviously,
the obvious answer is if you have to choose between which one
to make, you'd rather make the one with one. But okay, נפקא
מינה היכי דמשכחת לה nafka mina heichi d'mashkachat lah מופנה מצד אחד
ואינו מופנה כל עיקר. mufneh mitzad echad v'eino mufneh kol ikar. So
let's say you have a choice of two גזירות שוות. gezeirot shavot.
One that has zero words available and one that has one word
available. דלאו להאי אית ליה פירכא ולאו להאי אית ליה פירכא, D'lav
l'hai it lei pircha v'lav l'hai it lei pircha, and neither one
has a valid critique. So either one could be made and has
just in terms of the strength of the גזירה שוה, gezera shavas.
you know, in theory you could critique it but no critique is
available. So either one presents itself as a potential גזירה שוה gezeirah
shavah, to be made. So which one are you going to make?
שפיר טפי דאינו מופנה כל עיקר וגמרינן ממופנה מצד אחד, Shappir tefei
d'eino mufneh kol ikar v'gamrinan mimufneh mitzad echad, similar to what we
said before. Even if that we still prefer, we abandon the one
that has zero words available, go with the one that has one
word available. So here you see this is again, I'm sure this
does not keep you up at night but nevertheless,
it is interesting that it reveals the גמרא's Gemara somewhat recognition and
hesitation with the whole hermeneutic of גזירה שוה gezeirah shavah and puts
limits on it. That only you can really make it when both
words are available and anything less than that maybe you can make
it, it's open to critique and along with this it's saying even
if in theory you could make two you would obviously prefer the
one that argues that both words are extra and that's seen as
the biggest signal that a link is intended to be made and
therefore not open to critique.
What's interesting is that the whole thing starts by, at least in
the second פרק, perek, אלה תולדות שמים וארץ בהבראם וביום עשות ה'
אלהים ארץ ושמים. Eileh toldot shamayim v'aretz b'hibaram u'v'yom asot Hashem Elokim
eretz v'shamayim. So you know, it still used like those big general
words.
I know but the ארץ ושמים. eretz v'shamayim. Alright let's go on.
והא, V'ha, the גמרא Gemara says והא, v'ha, מאי פירכא איכא? mai
pircha ika? So anyway, what question could you have asked here? In
the end we didn't really say you could ask questions, we really
just said we prefer two over one. But nevertheless the גמרא Gemara
is saying at the end we're saying you do have two here
which makes it, you know, airtight. Which makes it, which means that
because you have both ויצר, vayitzer, both ends open, you can't ask
any questions. So that implies that in theory there is a logical
critique you could make and obviously there's a million ways you could
distinguish between humans and animals. So the גמרא Gemara just says one
of them. What critique could you have made? So the גמרא Gemara
says משום דאיכא למפרך מה לאדם שכן נתחייב במצוות. mishum d'ika l'mifrach
mah l'adam shekein nitchayev b'mitzvot. Okay, because since we're dealing about the
question and by you know, about in the end this is the
what is the purpose of linking humans to animals for רבי מאיר?
Rabbi Meir? To say if a fetus looks like an animal, it's
still considered to be a fetus for the הלכות halachot of childbirth.
So in the end it's about a world of טומאה וטהרה. tumah
v'taharah. So you could say maybe not, maybe since humans are generally
more susceptible to טומאה tumah than animals. Humans can become טמא, tamei,
animals cannot become. A dead animal is a source of טומאה tumah
but a live animal cannot become טמא. tamei. So therefore I could
say I'm not prepared to assume that if a fetus, a human
fetus looks like an animal that it should have the same laws
of טומאה. tumah. Animals in general have a smaller scope of laws
of טומאה tumah than humans and I'm not going to, and therefore
if it was open to critique it would have been an obvious
way to distinguish between them. But once the גזירה שוה gezeirah shavah
both words are free, then it's just saying don't ask questions. We're
using the גזירה שוה gezeirah shavah and therefore we're saying even if
it looks like an animal. Okay. So this whole discussion is telling
us
that when a woman aborts a fetus
that looks
like
an animal then that she still has the טומאה tumah of childbirth
according to רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. Because he sees these verbs as
linking them. Alright? And again for now I'm assuming that we're acknowledging
that it's a human fetus but the question is to what degree
does its appearance determine its הלכתי halachic status.
And is there, was there any
thought
that a woman who aborts something is not aborting a human fetus?
Well that's what I suggested before. I'm trying to resist that but
we're going to see in a few lines a גמרא Gemara that
seems to suggest that it might not even be human. But at
this stage I would like
to, that question would not be necessary.
Right, but I want us to remember what I consider to be
a very a very close analogy was the discussion around blood. That
even though certain things have biological realities and the גמרא Gemara said
if it's a blood that's green, blood that's white, it acknowledged it
might be blood, but it doesn't have that הלכתי halachic status if
it's not red. So the גמרא Gemara similarly could be acknowledging that
this is a human fetus biologically but it does not define the
woman as a יולדת yoledet if it does not look human. Okay?
So that's how I would, until now there is nothing that indicates
otherwise but let's see where we're going. Alright so now the גמרא
Gemara says like this: וכן אמר רבי חייא בר אבא אמר רבי
יוחנן היינו טעמא דרבי מאיר, v'chein amar Rabbi Chiyya bar Abba amar
Rabbi Yochanan hainu ta'ama d'Rabbi Meir, this is the reason of רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir that says even if it looks like. an animal,
הוא ונאמר בו יצירה כאדם ho vane'emar bo yetzirah ke'adam because by
animals it says יצירה yetzirah like it does by humans. אמר ליה
רב אמי, Amar lei Rav Ami, so said רב אמי Rav Ami
to him, אלא מעתה המפלת דמות תנין ella mei'ata hamapelet demut tannin
sort of got rid of תנין tannin which is maybe the biggest
question because it says ויברא. Vayivra. Now we're going to get questions
which are sort of feeling a little bit, a little more bizarre.
So if this is true, המפלת דמות הר, hamapelet demut har, let's
say the fetus looks like a mountain. So אם טמאה לידה, im
tmeia leida, let's say she'd be טמאה, tmeia, as it says כי
הנה יוצר הרים ובורא רוח, ki hinei yotzeir harim uvorei ruach, so
it said יצירה yetzirah by mountains, God fashions mountains. So you could
have said that's not מופנה, but no, that's what he does. He
says אמר ליה, amar lei, הר מי קא מפלת, har mi ka
mapelas, whatever would come out of a woman's body would not look
like a mountain. Okay, it might be mountain-shaped, triangular, but it doesn't
look, it's not a mountain. So
if you were describing it, you'd say it looks like a stone,
it looks triangular, you know, but you would, but you would not
say
that it looks like a mountain. So ההוא גוש קירי, hahu gush
krei, that's called like a chunk of dirt. It would not, so
you can't, it's not even a relevant question. Right, a blob. אלא
מעתה המפלת רוח, ella mei'ata hamapelet ruach, טמאה אם טמאה לידה, tmeia
im tmeia leida,
let's say she aborts wind. Now what does that mean? Well, actually
what does that mean, aborts wind? Passes gas? No, but it means
that the גמרא Gemara often actually discusses that when a woman aborts,
what happens if the embryonic sac is seen to sort of more
be filled with air and not really have so much substance in
it? So that seems to and it often describes that as רוח.
ruach. So what if, you know, what's coming out is really seems
to be something that's like, you know, air trapped in some embryonic
sac? So maybe רוח ruach is also considered יצירה. yetzirah.
So דכתיב ובורא רוח, dechtiv uvorei ruach, because the end of that
verse is and God creates רוח. ruach. And again we said that
בורא borei could in theory be an extra word. So וכי תימא
לא מופנה, vechi teima lo mufne, ah, that's not extra, you needed
the word בורא רוח borei ruach for doing its job in the
verse. No, מדהוה ליה למכתב יוצר הרים ורוח, mi'dehavah lei limchtav yotzeir
harim veruach, it could have said God fashions mountains and wind. So
the word, the verb בורא borei is extra. וכתיב ובורא רוח, uchtiv
uvorei ruach, so that's an extra word. שמע מינה לאפנויי, shma mina
lafnuyei, so it's free and let's go ahead and make the link.
So אמר ליה דנין דברי תורה מדברי תורה ואין דנין דברי תורה
מדברי קבלה. amar lei donin divrei torah midivrei torah ve'ein donin divrei
torah midivrei kabbalah. We'd rather learn, you know, biblical פסוקים psukim from
biblical פסוקים, psukim, you know, חומש Chumash from חומש. Chumash. You really
don't want to learn
גזירה שוה, gezeirah shavah right, from things that are not in the
five books. Michael says sometimes we do it, but often it's critiqued,
often we say that we're not really learning it from there, yeah,
the גמרא's Gemara not a hundred percent rigorous on that but that's
at least a general rule. Now one does wonder, so I said
let me go through for a second, one does wonder whether these
questions were asked really sincerely or whether they were type of like
reductio ad absurdum, meaning to sort of like say, look, it's not
just that the verse is extra, right? There's actually there's probably something
more going on here, some implicit argument that the animal appearance is
closer to a human appearance and therefore it's close enough to be
considered a human-like appearance. Because if all it was was a word
here, word there, you could come to these absurd conclusions. So maybe
that was the question, but at least the way the גמרא Gemara
answered it is it took it as a serious question and gave,
you know, gave a serious answer. But it's hard to know whether
the question was meant as a reductio ad absurdum or not. Charlie,
you had a question?
I was just going to say the same question. We do derive
Torah law from.
Yeah, whatever, the גמרא's Gemara not always rigorous, and very often when
it does, it says we're not really deriving, it's really we always
knew it and the פסוקים psukim are just revealing what we already
knew. Anyway, yes, the גמרא's Gemara not always consistent. The one final
thing, you
know, what was interesting is you know if you want to think
of it biologically, you know, or you almost want to compare it
to a fish because, you know, the fish is in water, the
embryonic sac, all the fluid.
Okay, so that's not where the גמרא's Gemara coming from. So now
the גמרא Gemara says like
this, רבה בר בר חנה אמר רבי יוחנן היינו טעמא דרבי מאיר,
Rabbah bar bar Chana amar Rebbi Yochanan hainu ta'ama de'Rebbi Meir, here's
the
reason of
רבי מאיר. Rebbi Meir. הוא ועיניהם דומות כשל אדם. ho ve'eineihem domot
keshel adam. Animal eyes, presumably vertebrate eyes, look similar to human. רש"י
Rashi says what this means is that the pupil is round and
apparently in a fish the pupil is more like, you know, is
that not true? Cats.
Yes, their eyes become a, their pupils become a slit when there's
a lot of light.
And when it's open, are they circular?
Eventually, but it takes a lot of light to do that.
And how about fish?
Fish eyes are actually the pupils are more round, it's like the
opposite.
Are they really?
Alright, anyway, we're not fish eyes are very different.
Alright, so let's see what it's reading into even location, the way
they face. גמרא's Gemara going to get to that. Now it's talking
about the eyes. And רש"י Rashi says it means the pupil. Okay,
how about the socket of the eye? The entire eye, the גמרא
Gemara will get to. Okay, so that's the answer. Let's see what
it says. So anyway it's saying there's actually something about the face
that's similar. It's also interesting the power of the eyes, you know,
to like the eyes are the window into the soul, you know,
seeing something in someone's eyes. It's an interesting question in general, you
know, about the whole way we identify humanity with the
face and, you know, and so and so this whole thing about.
it's like identity of this thing and what to be considered a
human fetus has to do with to what degree its facial features
are similar and then focusing in on the eyes. So let's take
a look. I actually often thought about this I'll just say,
the whole issue around brain death and organ donation and some people
like argue well, you know, like if a person even if they're
brain dead, you know, the fact that they can, you know, bring
a baby to, you know, a fetus to gestation should show that
it's alive, you know, and but they did an experiment in Israel
to sort of show the rabbis when they were having this issue
that they took a pregnant pig, not pig, a sheep, and they
cut off its head and they kept it alive long enough, well
they kept the blood flowing and the heart pumping long enough for
it to deliver. You know, so they said, you know, and I,
you know, and I don't think anybody would argue if you had
like a decapitated human, but was kept somehow medically the body was
kept the blood flowing and the, you know, oxygen going so that
fetus could gestate, nobody would say that reality of just holding a
fetus and gestating it makes it human. There's something very powerful about
the head and the face and the face, you know, being there
and being intact and looking human that I think, you know, very,
you know, sort of says yeah, that the person is still alive
if they can do this and they've got their head on then
they're alive, but if they can do that without their head on
even though they're brain dead, somehow, you know, that then they're no
longer human. So there's something very powerful about that whole the face
and the head.
Yes, there's a book called Human that's put out by the Smithsonian
and DK Books and it has several versions of the cover and
one is just an eye.
Aha, interesting. Okay, so so let's take a look. So that's the
גמרא's Gemara argument. The eyes are the same.
The purpose of all of this is to connect the fetus to
a living
to say that a fetus that does not look human but has
but looks animal-like is that presumably now we're honing in on the
face, is that considered to be a human birth even if it
has if it doesn't even look
human? For purposes of טומאה. tumah. Right. Right. So let's take a
look at what the גמרא Gemara says. וכי תימא, Vechai teima,
so the גמרא Gemara says like this, הא בעיניה כשל אדם. Ho
be'eina keshel adam. אלא מעתה סייעתא גמרא מפלס דמות נחש באמו טמאה
לידה, Ela me'ata se'ita Gemara mephelas demut nachash be'imo tme'a leda, הא
בגלגל עינו עגולה כשל אדם. Ho begalgal eino agula keshel adam.
So how about if it looks like a snake that she should
be טמאה tme'a because the גמרא Gemara says that the eyes of
a snake look like that of a human? Again I'm assuming like
רש"י Rashi it means the pupil. You be able to tell me
if that's true or not. But וכי תימא Vechai teima Charlie, do
snake eyes, their pupils look like you don't know? I don't know
how a snake looks. וכי תימא הכא נמי, Vechai teima hacha nami,
that's true. ואי נחש, Ve'ee nachash, why isn't it in the משנה?
Mishna? So אי
תנא נחש, Ee tanachash, if it said a snake, הוה אמינא בנחש
הוא דפלגי רבנן עליה דרבי מאיר, havei amina benachash hu depalgei rabbanan
alei de'Rabbi Meir, that's where the rabbis argue because doesn't because דלא
כתיב ביה יצירה de'lo ketiv bei yetzira because it doesn't have the
even the verb יצר, yetzer, אבל בהמה וחיה, aval behema vechaya,
maybe they would agree by that דכתיב ביה יצירה de'ketiv bei yetzira
maybe they would agree. So therefore what the גמרא's Gemara really saying
it's conceding the point. If it's about what it looks like and
we're going to focus on the eyes, then according to רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir it would not be limited to בהמה חיה ועוף behema
chaya ve'of or mammals and birds, it would include snakes. But it
wasn't mentioned in the משנה Mishna so you shouldn't be distracted and
think that the rabbis only argued on the snake case. Okay, so
now the גמרא Gemara says one minute, וגבי מומין קתני לה, vegabei
mumim katanila, if an animal's eye looks like a human eye, that's
considered a מום mum in an animal if it has if it
looks like a human eye, which proves that it normally doesn't. Because
what does the משנה Mishna say in בכורות? Bechorot? איזה שגלגל עינו
עגול כשל אדם, Eizeh shegagal eino agol keshel adam, if the if
the if the eyeball of an animal is round like a human
then it is a מום mum if an animal's eye looks like
human's eye. So so clearly it normally doesn't look like human's eye.
So גמרא Gemara says לא קשיא lo kashya it's not difficult. הא
באוכמא הא בצירייא. Ha be'uchma ha betziraya.
One is in the black, the other is in the the way
רש"י Rashi reads it is in the sort of the what do
you call it like when you put a stone inside a setting?
So anyways, one is in the eye socket essentially, the whole shape
of the eye. So the black of the eye, the pupil of
the eye looks the same, this is the way רש"י Rashi reads
it again I don't know if it's true I didn't check, but
the whole shape of the entire eye of humans is different than
it is by animals. Charlie, anything to add to that? Anyways, that's
the argument. So yes, there's a part that looks like human, there's
a part that not, and the one that says it's a מום
mum when it looks like human is talking about the entire eye
socket, the entire shape of the eye. רבי ינאי אמר, Rabbi Yannai
amar, so that's one reason focusing in on the eye. רבי ינאי
Rabbi Yannai says היינו טעמא דרבי מאיר hainu ta'ama de'Rabbi Meir this
is the reason of רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, הואיל ועיניהם הולכות לפניהם
כשל אדם. ho ve'eineihem holchos lephaneihem keshel adam. This is what Michael
said. The eyes are in front like humans as opposed to fish
eyes which are on the side. Why are you nodding your head
Charlie?
A lot of animals that's not the case.
Okay, so let's see what the גמרא Gemara says.
So the גמרא Gemara honed in on bird because birds was mentioned
in the משנה. Mishna. And birds clearly it's the you know not
the case.
Not though some some are in front
well that's what the גמרא Gemara is going to say. So the
גמרא Gemara says all right, באותן עוף שאין עיניו הולכות לפניו, be'otan
of she'ein einav holchos lephanav, how about a bird that the eyes
are usually on the
side? וקאמר רבי מאיר דמטמאים veka'amar Rabbi Meir de'mitammen
רבי מאיר... Rabbi Meir... So an owl, actually an owl face is
very human-like and therefore oh, so when he says birds he doesn't
mean all birds, he just means owls, okay? He says birds but
he really means if it looks like an owl. If it looks
like other birds, no, only if it looks like, when it comes
to birds, only if it looks like an owl. So the גמרא
Gemara says מאי שנא בהמה וחיה דאינהו חזות פניהם כשל אדם? mai
shna behema vechaya de'inhu chazut peneihem keshel adam? I'm sorry, did I
miss a line? ובשאר עופות לא? uv'sh'ar ofot lo? Would you say
by other birds not? מיתיבי. meitivei. I'll ask you this. רבי חנינא
בן אנטיגנוס אומר, Rabbi Chanina ben Antignos omer, whoever it is, רבי
חנינא בן גמליאל אומר, Rabbi Chanina ben Gamliel omer, ניראין דברי רב
מאיר בבהמה וחיה. nirin divrei Rav Meir b'vehema v'chaya. I am, I'm
inclined to rule like רב מאיר Rav Meir when it comes to
like mammals, ודברי חכמים בעופות, v'divrei Chachamim b'ofot, and like the rabbis
that it's not considered a human birth when it comes to birds.
מאי עופות? mai ofot? What does he mean birds? אילימא בבקייא וקיפופא,
ilima b'vekaya vekipopa, if he means like owls, so why is he
more inclined one over the other? מאי שנא בהמה וחיה דאינהו חזות
פניהם כשל אדם, mai shna behema vechaya de'inhu chazut peneihem keshel adam,
why is he more inclined to say animals, an animal appearance is
considered human-like because there their eyes go in front of them? So
בקייא וקיפופא נמי, bekaya vekipopa nami, so by owls as well. So
אלא פשיטא, ela pshita, if he thinks that he rules against רב
מאיר Rav Meir by birds, there must be something different about birds.
What's different? בשאר עופות, bishar ofot, birds that are not owls, that
the eyes are on the side. So if he's saying that there
he rules against רב מאיר Rav Meir by other birds, it implies
that רב מאיר Rav Meir applies his law to all birds, bird-like
appearance. מכלל דרב מאיר פליגי בשאר עופות. m'klal d'Rav Meir pligi b'shar
ofot. It sounds like Rabbi, he's saying I don't like רב מאיר'ס
Rav Meir's position by birds. So the גמרא Gemara assumes the only
reason to distinguish birds from the others is because of the eyes
on the side. So it sounds like רב מאיר, Rav Meir, when
he says his law, says that even by a bird appearance where
the eyes are on the side. So the גמרא Gemara says no,
חסורי מחסרא והכי קתני, chasuri mechasra vehachi katani, you have some words
missing, here's how you have to, you have to switch the text
a little. Here's how you have to read it. רבי חנינא בן
גמליאל אומר, Rabbi Chanina ben Gamliel omer, ניראין דברי רב מאיר בבהמה
וחיה, nirin divrei Rav Meir b'vehema v'chaya, it really רב מאיר'ס Rav
Meir's ruling makes sense by mammals, והוא הדין בבקייא וקיפופא, vehu hadin
b'vekaya vekipopa, and the same by owls, ודברי חכמים בשאר עופות, v'divrei
Chachamim b'shar ofot, and it seems like the rabbis that it's not
considered human when it looks like other birds. Why? שאף רב מאיר
לא נחלק עמהם אלא בבקייא וקיפופא, sh'af Rav Meir lo nechelak imahem
ela b'vekaya vekipopa, because really רב מאיר Rav Meir anyway never applied
his law by other types of birds, he only applied his law
by an owl appearance. אבל בשאר עופות מודי להו, aval b'shar ofot
modei lehu, but by other animals he would agree. So this is
very interesting because very often like the גמרא, Gemara, you know, gives
different reasons and there's like not a clear difference between what reason
you would adopt. But here the גמרא Gemara is very consistent. It
says if we base it on the verse, then it's just חיה
בהמה ועוף, chaya behema veof, but it's everything in that category. You
know, it suggests sea monsters, חס ושלום, chas veshalom, another verse that
it rules it out. But here it's saying if you go by
appearance, oh, let's talk about different things. Maybe snakes have circular eyes,
maybe some birds yes and some birds no. If it's about the
eyes on the side, eyes in the front. So if it's really
about appearance, it would depend on which, you know, on how much
is the appearance actually similar to a person's.
We're totally away from the verse.
We're, yeah, it's a completely different approach. The interesting thing is you
can always, essentially focus on something else.
That's true, and the גמרא Gemara will, but this is what the
גמרא Gemara is choosing to focus on. So, yes.
I don't really understand,
I don't really understand
why we need this whole discussion.
If it comes out of the woman, yes,
then they have to make a decision about the status, correct, of
the woman, I guess, right, and the fetus, right?
Well, that's an interesting question, like is the fetus considered to
have טומאת מת tumas meis or whatever? Is that related to this
discussion? For now let's assume no. Let's assume it's just a question
about the woman.
And there are many maybe legitimate considerations, right, but the last thing
that I think should dictate what any status is is what the
fetus looks like. I mean, it's crazy. They didn't know anything about
development. It's not even possible that a woman, I mean, what is
the, what is the message about what women do when, when you
suggest that what comes out of a woman is not human?
So, so you mean like if you say, oh, this thing even
though it was developed three months isn't a problem because it's not
even really, doesn't even really look human, then it's also dehumanizing the
woman in the process.
Yes, let's put aside that there's nothing in here about the emotional
experience, right, that this isn't being dealt with in the law in
anyway. Okay, but that's not about, we know those feelings. That's fine.
We know this is a law, legal...
that's fine, I'm okay...
that's fine, it's all right. Yes, okay.
But just from the perspective of law, right, just from the legal
perspective, the thing that should determine it is
is that it came out of the woman, period.
So, let me ask you a question. So, okay, I totally hear
that. I totally hear that and I certainly hear the point that
as soon as you're sort of dismissive,
dismissing the significance of this
fetus... But but I don't think that that appearance should be so
should be irrelevant, like would you have the same type of reaction
to the idea that even if blood comes out if it doesn't
have certain colors maybe it doesn't make her טמאה? tameiah? One second,
who cares? It's coming from the woman, it's blood, we shouldn't make
those types of distinctions.
Now
given the anatomy that was presented with body parts that I don't
recognize,
you know, the answer to that question would be it would have
made life simpler because I think the focus in trying to do
that
there's a way in which it creates obsessional thinking that that is
more harmful in the end than helpful
because there's like this maybe there's a chance that this particular stain
is okay.
You know, at the end of the day it leads to a
lot of leniencies, it leads to a lot of times that a
woman isn't a נדה. niddah. But
and here too these distinctions lead to a woman not being a
יולדת. yoledet.
It's not worth it.
I see. Seth, what you were going to say something?
I think this is their way not directly of addressing
developmental.
Yes, but the גמרא Gemara makes distinctions between before 40 days and
after 40 days and this before 40 days doesn't a problem no
matter what it looks like. After 40 days you can still get
out of it if it doesn't look like it doesn't have human
appearance.
I guess it depends on the level of development what I mean
I have no idea about biology but what what the fetus will
look like and so maybe that's what they were actually addressing indirectly.
Yeah but the גמרא Gemara could I mean according to the גמרא
Gemara it could be eight months developed and if it has this
animal-like appearance it's not a problem.
It's not. That seems to be really exploring whether this could be
an animal fetus.
Not yet. I I will agree to that in the next
line that implies that a woman slept with an animal to
produce a or that there was some genetic aberration. I don't think
the גמרא Gemara is ever
actually anyway but I hear that, I hear that, but it hasn't
said that yet. It'll say that in the next sentence. It hasn't
said it yet. Okay
until now it's just said it looks like an animal. The possibility
that it is an animal is coming up.
All right so that's sort of dehumanizing the woman of sleeping.
Yeah again I'm not sure they're going that far but certainly the
dehumanizing aspect I hear. All right we have to move on. You'll
if you'll get the what you just said in a minute.
Yes there is a sensitivity to the developmental stages, you know, ontogeny
phylogeny so the point where the human has a tail has different
aspects
and
so maybe that's what they were actually addressing at the earliest
stage and not later.
I hear that. I hear that, that's what Seth was saying. Okay
let's
get back to the דף. Thank you. Okay David made a good
point which is similar to what Seth was saying which is that
you know maybe it's more months developed but it might be arrested
development and therefore look like you know have these appearances. But I
do understand that the whole idea of sort of emphasizing the animal
identity is very disturbing and that's going to come up particularly in
the next sentence. So let's see it. Okay so the גמרא Gemara
says like
this והתניא ve-ha-tanya did we not teach in a ברייתא braita אמר
רבי אלעזר בר צדוק amar Rabbi Elazar bar Tzadok המפלת מין בהמה
וחיה ha-mapelt min behemah va-chayah לדברי רבי מאיר le-divrei Rabbi Meir ולד.
vlad. Now
here is where it becomes really problematic because it does say מין
בהמה וחיה. min behemah va-chayah. It says do we not teach in
a ברייתא braita that a woman who miscarries a בהמה וחיה? behemah
va-chayah? So here it's not saying it looks like, it's saying she
miscarries an animal. Okay רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says it is a
ולד, vlad, it is a fetus, ולדברי חכמים
אינו ולד. u-le-divrei chachamim eino vlad. ובעופות u-ve-ofot and when it comes
to birds תבדק tibbadek you have to check. So what are you
checking for? It means some type of birds are a problem and
some are not. So למאן תבדק le-man tibbadek who are you checking
according to? לאו לדברי רבי מאיר lav le-divrei Rabbi Meir are you
not checking according to רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir דאמר d'amar קיר וקפופא
kir ve-kippofa אין in שאר עופות shear ofot לא. lo.
So it sounds like this exactly proves
what we are saying
that it says that if it looks like a bird then it
depends. So it means it depends if it looks like an owl
then רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir would say fine that has a status,
if it doesn't look like it not. So you see again even
for רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir there's a distinction between what type of
bird it looks like. But here we actually so the גמרא Gemara
says אמר רב אמי בריה דרב איקא amar Rav Ami berei de-Rav
Ika לא lo תבדק tibbadek לרבנן le-rabbanan maybe it maybe the rabbis
would actually agree even though the rabbis say if it looks like
an animal no maybe they would say if it looks like a
bird particularly an owl maybe they would even concede that case. Maybe
looking like an owl is better than looking like various mammals and
animals. Why? So yes דאמרי d'amri maybe they say קיר וקפופא kir
ve-kippofa אין in שאר עופות shear ofot לא. lo. I'm sorry did
I say that? That they would say yes by an owl not
by other birds. Why?
ומה ישנא u-mai shna קיר וקפופא kir ve-kippofa מבהמה וחיה mi-behemah va-chayah
why might the rabbis even concede the owl why might that be
better than looking like various mammals and animals? הואיל ויש להן ריסא.
ho'il ve-yesh lahen risa. לסתות כאדם *listot k'adam* because they have cheeks.
So they don't only have eyes, they have a very human type
of a face, you know they have like cheeks and the whole
sort of shape of the face. So maybe even the rabbis would
concede that case. So you can't prove that רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
*Rabbi Meir* distinguishes by birds, maybe it's the opposite, maybe the rabbis
would concede the case of the owls because of their very human
appearance. But Rivka, but here it becomes very problematic because it didn't
say כמין *kemin*, it looks like, it said חיה ועוף *chaya va'of*
and we're going about to see the next halakhic question which really
sort of seems to bring that possibility home.
Yes, Charlie. Artscroll must be uncomfortable with that. They translate המפלת מין
בהמה וחיה *chamaphelet min beheima vachaya* as if a woman aborts an
object resembling...
yeah, obviously, obviously, right. So, but I'm just saying obviously, I understand
and
that's not what the פשט *pshat* is.
I understand. Let's read the next sentence. Okay. So the Gemara says
like
this: בעי מיניה רב ירמיה מרבי זירא *ba'ei minei Rav
Yirmiyah meivrav Zeira*, לרבי מאיר דאמר בהמה במעי אשה ולד vlad, מעליא
הוא *l'Rabbi Meir d'amar beheima b'mei isha vlad me'alya hu*.
Okay, there you go, right, an animal in the mother's womb, that's
a ולד vlad *vlad* that רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir *Rabbi Meir* can
mean בהמה *beheima*. Now you could say that the Gemara is using
shorthand, right, it's easier to say בהמה *beheima* than say something that
looks like a בהמה *beheima*. But again, you know, it's becoming more
suggestive that the Gemara is thinking that this might actually be, you
know, not just looking like an animal but an animal. Now I
don't know if I'd go as far as Rivka says that it
suggests bestiality. It might just suggest genetic aberration, you know,
of an animal?
Yeah, I mean the Gemara talks, when we learned בכורות Bechorot *Bechoros*,
the Gemara talked about, you know, a cow giving birth to something
that looks like a sheep and all that type of thing.
That's a good point, that Greek mythology has stories like Leda and
the swan... the
swan was Zeus in disguise.
Right, right. Okay, alright. Alright, now not only is it the, I
get it, not only is it the language that it's saying בהמה
*beheima*, not looks like a בהמה *beheima*, let's look at what the
question is. Okay, בהמה במעי אשה ולד מעליא הוא *beheima b'mei isha
vlad me'alya hu*. According to רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir *Rabbi Meir* says
that this animal in the mother's womb is considered a fetus. קיבל
בה אביה קידושין kiddushin מהו *kibbel bah aviha kiddushin mahu*.
Let's say the father tried to marry off this fetus, assuming that
a father can marry off his daughter before she's born, okay, and
then
it's a daughter,
and assuming it's right, it's a daughter, and then it's born and
it's this בהמה *beheima* or a בהמה *beheima* looking like thing. Is
it a valid קידושין kiddushin *kiddushin*? Okay, that's the question.
Is it aborted or not aborted?
So the Gemara is, that's going to be the answer, the Gemara
is imagining in the question, I have to... okay, we have to
cut down on certainly on the side comments, we only have 10
minutes left, the Gemara is imagining in the question that it could
actually be born viable, and that's going to be the... let's take
a look at the answer. Okay. So the Gemara says למאי נפקא
מינא *l'mai nafka mina*? What do I care? לצוררה באחותה *l'tzorei b'achosah*,
let's say, you know, if you did this act, would you then
be able to be married her sister, you know, obviously the Gemara's
going to assume that this animal won't live for long, so there's
not a big נפקא מינא *nafka mina* or this thing won't live
for long, there's not a big נפקא מינא *nafka mina* about are
you considered married to it, but the question is, okay, but then
what's your status vis-a-vis the siblings, you know, so let's see what
the Gemara's answer is. So the Gemara says למימרא דחיי *l'meimra dechayei*?
That sounds like it's going to live. Because the way רש"י *Rashi*
says anyway, you know,
a wife's sister is only אסור *assur* while the wife is alive.
והאמר רב יהודה אמר רב לא אמר רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir אלא
הואיל ובמינו מתקיים *v'ha amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav lo amar Rabbi
Meir ela ho'il b'mino miskayyem*. The only reason רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
*Rabbi Meir* said it is because analogous things live, meaning a real
animal is viable. So even though this fetus is not viable, it's
still... it's still... it's still considered a fetus because things that look
like it, real animals, are viable. So the point being here now,
the really the emphasis being that the Gemara's saying but it itself
is not viable. Okay, the type of thing it looks like is
viable, but it itself is not viable. So the Gemara says the
question is moot because this thing will never live. Now, a number
of ראשונים *Rishonim* ask, but what do you mean? Even if the
thing won't live,
you know, how about is the man forbidden
in the... you know... to marry the mother? Because that doesn't require
the prohibition of mother and daughter doesn't require that the daughter is
still alive and there's other halakhic נפקא מינות *nafka minas*. So the
ראשונים *Rishonim* say, no, no, no, when we say it's not viable,
what it means is that obviously you can't do קידושין kiddushin, *kiddushin*
on something that will never be viable. Okay, the possibility that the
father could accept קידושין kiddushin *kiddushin* for his daughter who's a fetus
would only be a viable fetus, a fetus that we would say
is never viable, it wouldn't be relevant to it. Now I would
say, here's the question about how you think about the issue, because...
and we'll read this in a minute, you could say, you know,
on the one hand, it calls it בהמה *beheima*, a בהמה *beheima*.
But on the other hand, the fact that it's talking about is,
you know, what's the validity of the
קידושין kiddushin *kiddushin*... Should we consider it a human, and is the
קידושין kiddushin binding or not, and maybe that's exactly the question of
are you calling this thing human or not? So let's see where
the גמרא Gemara comes through with this. So אמר רב אחא בריה
דרב יעקב Amar Rav Aha brei d'Rav Yaakov עד כאן הביא ר'
ירמיה לר' זירא לידי גיחוך. Ad kan hivi Rabbi Yirmiyah l'Rabbi Zeira
l'yadei gichuch.
So ר' ירמיה Rabbi Yirmiyah was trying to, or almost brought him,
because means trying to, get ר' זירא Rabbi Zeira to laugh ולא
גחיך, v'lo gachich, and he didn't laugh. So that's sort of the
question of he was trying to ask him an absurd question. So
what's absurd about it? Is it absurd that he considered this thing
to be
an animal and maybe קידושין won't be binding because maybe it'll be
an animal, and that he could actually consider something growing in a
mother's womb to have the status of an animal? Or was it
absurd the other way? Was it absurd because he considered it to
maybe be human and maybe the קידושין would be binding? Not exactly
clear what, or maybe just the whole question is humorous
anyway. But anyway, this question, I think, gets really bizarre. It's calling
it an animal. It raises this question. On the one hand, one
side of the question clearly is saying you have the halachic applications
of daughter, human, and so on, and that side says okay, but
it's not viable. But the question is, what's on the other side
of the question? The other side of the question implicitly seems to
be maybe it has a status of an animal. Now if you
think that that's crazy, I want you to look quickly at תוספות
Tosafot where
תוספות Tosafot
says לציורי באחותו. l'tzayurei b'achoto. תוספות Tosafot says לענין גופו לא בעי
אם הבא עליו חייב משום אשת איש או אם חייב הריגה דפשיטא
ליה דאינו חייב וכו׳ L'inyan gufo lo bei im haba alav chayav
mishum eshet ish o im chayav hariga d'pshita lei d'eino chayav etc.
Anyway, I'm not interested in that. And then he said, like two
lines from the end of this תוספות, Tosafot, ומיהו הוי מצי למיבעי
אם הרובעו חייב סקילה כדין הבא על בהמה. u'mihu havay matzi l'mibaya
im harove'o chayav sekila k'din haba al behema. It could have asked
at the moment the גמרא Gemara thought that this thing could be
born viable, if somebody had sex with this thing, forget קידושין, would
it be considered bestiality? So you see according to תוספות Tosafot that
was exactly, right, that was exactly the question: is this fetus human
or animal? So one side of it is is קידושין binding? The
other side is would there be an act of bestiality? Right? The
רא״ש Rosh says maybe the question is does it cause
corpse טומאת מת? tumat met? Right? We even talked about the status
of the mother, what about whether it's considered to be a human
corpse once it's miscarried? So here you really do see exactly, while
you could have before this, I think, argued that it was just
about appearances and a technical הלכה halacha thing, here it seems very
much at least the question is raising the possibility of thinking of
it as an animal. Now you could always try to say that's
why it was absurd and he was laughing, that he would, that
the answer's what an absurd point, of course it's not. Right? But
he refused to laugh, he didn't take the
bait, but it didn't mean that the question wasn't absurd. Okay, but
תוספות Tosafot really, really problematizes it. You can't get more explicit than
that תוספות. Tosafot. Okay, so let's now continue. Yes.
Was there such realities to things in
the contemporary times, does a woman ever give birth to something that
would describe...
I don't know, I mean...
but is there some, really, was this a
reality or this whole thing just hypothetical?
There are unfortunately some serious defects that can look really bad.
Right. I just want to end this by reading the רא״ש. Rosh.
If you look at the תוספות הרא״ש, Tosfot HaRosh, the small writing
on the side, and you go up five lines from the bottom,
about a third in, he says והא דלא מצי למיבעי כזית ממנו
מטמא באהל או כשעורה מטמא. v'ha d'lo matzi l'mibaya k'zayit mimeno mitame
b'ohel o k'seora mitami. Why didn't they ask whether it has the
טומאה tumah of a human corpse? Right? If the question is human
versus animal, is it טומאת מת? tumat met? So he says no,
דמלתא דפשיטא היא כיון דדמות אדם הולידה, d'milta d'pshita hi kivan d'dmut
adam holida, it's obvious, since according to ר' מאיר Rabbi Meir the
mother is considered to be a יולדת, yoledet, it's considered to be
a ולד, so טמא כמו נפל, tame k'mo nefel, that it does
have the status of a human corpse and it is the status
of a מת. met. So according to him that was never the
question. Clearly it has a human status, it's clearly going to be
considered a human corpse, so we might have a question about I
don't know does קידושין work, but we're never really considering that it's
an animal, so clearly it has human status. But again, the language
of the question is very troublesome here in this section of the
גמרא.
Gemara. What about the קידושין on someone that's not born yet?
Well,
that goes to a whole question about דבר שלא בא לעולם davar
shelo ba l'olam and according to ר' מאיר Rabbi Meir yes, so
possibly. Enough to raise this question, possibly.
If it's a divorced woman's daughter?
No, if the mother's already pregnant and the fetus is viable, then
the answer is possibly. It depends on other issues. Okay, let's see,
let's read a little bit more in the גמרא, Gemara, at least
turn the page. גופא, Gufa, אמר רב יהודה אמר רב לא אמר
ר' מאיר אלא הואיל ומינו מתקיים. Amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav lo
amar Rabbi Meir ela ho'il u'mino mitkayem. This whole case of this
fetus really is not won't survive, is not viable, but it's enough
that it types of what it looks like is a type of
a thing that will survive in other cases. So אמר ר' ירמיה
מיתיבי, Amar Rabbi Yirmiyah mitivi, אף אנן נמי תנינא af anan nami
tanina that this won't live, I mean not that במינו מתקיים bimino
mitkayem but the reality that it itself will never be viable because
what do המפלת כמין בהמה חיה ועוף Hamapeles k'min beheimah chayah va-of
that when we have a list of there's a list in בכורות
of types of childbirth that a mother could have or miscarriages that
the next child will still be the בכור bechor for the נחלה
nachala for inheritance gets double portion but will not be a בכור
bechor for the פדיון הבן. pidyon haben. Why not? Because there's different
categories. For פדיון הבן pidyon haben the question is were you the
one that sort of breached the womb? So that is literally the
question about who came out first whereas for who gets the double
portion it's only the first viable child gets a double portion. So
if a woman miscarried not a
non-viable child meaning not a miscarriage normal miscarriage in theory it could
have been viable but it just was
miscarried then the next child does not get the double portion. But
if it was a fetus that was never viable then the next
child does get the double portion. Okay is that clear? If the
fetus didn't live but was viable in theory could have lived then
the next child will get the double portion. If it was never
viable he will not. So what is the case of never viable
or viable but miscarried? So we're going to say exactly this okay?
So המפלת כמין בהמה חיה ועוף Hamapeles k'min beheimah chayah va-of so
if it looks like an animal so רבי מאיר would say even
though I say that that's considered a ולד and a fetus and
so on I will still say it was such such a fetus
is never viable and therefore the second child will still get the
double portion. דברי רבי מאיר Divrei Rabbi Meir that's what רבי מאיר
says. So you see that he says that it's never viable it
was never viable. וחכמים אומרים עד שיהיה בו מצורת אדם. Ve-Chachamim omrim
ad she-yei bo mi-tzurat adam. No it has to have the human
appearance. The same issue meaning they would say not of course they'd
agree that the second child gets a double portion but they would
even say that the second birth is a בכור bechor for פדיון
הבן pidyon haben because they basically say again the same argument. רבי
מאיר says yes this is a miscarriage it's a birth so the
second child doesn't get פדיון הבן pidyon haben but it was never
viable so the second child gets a double portion. וחכמים Ve-Chachamim say
like they say here it's not considered a birth and therefore the
second child not only gets a double portion but you have a
פדיון הבן. pidyon haben. And let's just finish this point just get
to the end of this ברייתא braita or משנה mishna actually והמפלת
סנדל ve-hamapeles sandal
if the child is sort of like flattened like a סנדל sandal
או שליא או שפיר מרוקם o shilya o shafir merukam or a
placenta or some type of a formed fetus but some type of
like it's beginning to get its color and its shape. I won't
get into details describe that right now. ויצא מחתך V'yatzah mechutach or
if it comes out dismembered. In those cases we say all of
those things whether it has a human appearance but it was a
miscarriage was viable at one time but just miscarried and therefore the
second child does not get the double portion. So in those cases
הבא אחריו בכור לנחלה haba acharav bechor le-nachala
excuse me did I say it right?
No no no I'm sorry in those cases a minute עד שיהיה
בו מצורת אדם המפלת סנדל או שליא או שפיר מרוקם ויצא מחתך
הבא אחריו בכור לנחלה ואינו בכור לכהן. ad she-yei bo mi-tzurat adam
hamapeles sandal o shilya o shafir merukam v'yatzah mechutach haba acharav bechor
le-nachala ve-eino bechor le-Kohen. I'm sorry
in those cases it also was not viable excuse me excuse me
in those cases it also was not viable and therefore the one
afterwards does get the double portion but again it is not a
פדיון הבן. pidyon haben. And just what is the point of bringing
this down? ואי סלקא דעתך דחי Ve-i salka deitach d'chai if you
think that such an a thing could have could possibly be viable
then הבא אחריו בכור לנחלה מי הוי haba acharav bechor le-nachala mi
havei the second child would not get a double portion because as
long even if it's miscarried if it was potentially viable then the
second child would not have a double portion. So you see according
to רבי מאיר these animal-like things were never viable. אמר רבא Amar
Rava Rava just tries to argue this. No לעולם דחי l'olam d'chai
I could have argued that these animal-like things are potentially viable and
so why does the second child still get a double portion? ושני
התם דאמר קרא ראשית אונו. U-shani hatam d'amar kra reishit ono. Who
gets the double portion? The first of his strength. Here the דרשה
drasha is what is אונו? ono? מי שלבו דוה עליו mi she-libo
daven alav a type of child here talking about that the father
is pained by the fact that it would be that it was
miscarried. Dealing with this yes but not in the way you might
like. Father's pain? Yes וזה שאין לבו דוה עליו. ve-zeh she-ein libo
daven alav. So here again the sort of dehumanizing of it it's
saying right if it has
this appearance oh well then nobody is sort of mourning its loss
and therefore it would not have an impact for the questions. No
one? The father. And therefore would not have an impact for those
laws. So the גמרא's Gemara point here is according just to wrap
it up according to רבי מאיר there is תורת לידה torat leida
the גמרא Gemara seems to suggest that it could even be considered
an animal but possibly that was the other side but it seems
but it hope we can certainly read the answer that it's considered
that absurd and it rejects it but even though it is considered
to be a miscarriage it was never considered to be viable and
because of that for example this הלכה halacha about the second child
and so on because it's a miscarriage the second child doesn't get
פדיון הבן pidyon haben as opposed but because it was never viable
the second child Still get a double portion. All right, we'll end
with that.